Dance Theater of Nepal collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Dance Theater of Nepal collection, 1996-2010
AFC 2011/002
Dance Theater of Nepal
Kapoor, Raj, 1968
Handlin, Sherry Onna
1601 items (6 containers, 3 linear feet).
1050 manuscript materials (3 containers)
7 sound disc (CD): digital; 4 3/4 in.
5 videocassettes (VHS): sound, color; 3/4 in.
32 videodiscs (DVD): digital; 4 3/4 in.
220 photographs: prints, black and white, color.
18 slides: color; 35 mm.
1 optical disc (63 color photographs on CD-R, jpegs files): digital; 1 3/4 in.
10 posters: black and white, color.
175 computer files (.jpegs) on 1 thumb drive; 3 1/2 in.
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Audiovisual, photographic, and manuscript documentation of classical and folk dance events and other activities sponsored by the Dance Theater of Nepal.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Handlin, Sherry Onna; Kapoor, Raj, 1968-
Organizations
Dance Theater of Nepal
Subjects
Dance--Nepal.; Folk dancing, Nepali--United States.; Nepali Americans--New York (State)--New York--Social life and customs.
Places
Nepal--Social life and customs.
Form/Genre
Color slides.; Manuscripts.; Photographs.; Posters.; Sound recordings.; Video recordings.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: 1. Manuscripts; 2. Sound Recordings; 3. Graphic Materials; 4. Moving Images. Materials are described at folder level.
Acquisition
Sherry Onna Handlin; 2011
Accruals
Further accruals are expected.
Related Material
The Dance Theater of Nepal Records, 1996-2005, Jerome Robbins Dance Division, New York Public Library: http://archives.nypl.org/dan/19829
The Dance Theater of Nepal Records, 1996-2013, New York State Library: http://www.nysl.nysed.gov/msscfa/sc23281.htm.
Access and Restrictions
Collection is open for research; access to collection materials may be restricted. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
See Folder 1 for additional information as stipulated by the donors.
Biographical/Organizational Note
The Dance Theater of Nepal, formerly known as the Raj Kapoor Ensemble, has been performing in the United States since its formation in 1996. The dance company assumed its present name in 1997 and became incorporated in 2001. The group's main focus is to preserve, to present, and to offer cultural instruction of Nepali performing arts to the United States and abroad. It is one of the first ensembles to bring the Nepali tradition into the mainstream. The group has performed at many nationally recognized cultural institutions and universities including the Smithsonian Institution, the Rubin Museum of Art, and Princeton University, and many others worldwide.
Raj Kapoor, dance and musical director of the Dance Theater of Nepal, is a Nepali native and a key figure in introducing Nepali heritage through traditional folk dance musical forms. Prior to creating the dance group, Kapoor was the associate director of Dramatic Art at the Royal Nepal Academy in Kathmandu, Nepal. In 1998, Kapoor, along with Sherry Onna Handlin, collaborated and created a year-long festival which celebrated and highlighted Nepali’s culture in America. As a dancer, musician, composer, and director, Kapoor participated in numerous productions performing in more than 23 countries worldwide. Kapoor has composed Nepali music for many films, television, and radio shows in United States, as well as in Nepal and India.
Sherry Onna Handlin earned a Bachelor of Fine Arts degree from the Pratt Institute, where she also taught courses. Sherry always had a keen interest in South Asian culture and in 1995, after a trip to North India and Nepal, her interest deepened and she became more involved with Himalayan performing arts. As the project director for the Dance Theater of Nepal, Sherry has made significant contributions to the group. Her work as an artist became even more notable when she performed the sacred Buddhist dance of Nepal "Charya Nritya." Sherry has also participated in many events that showcase Nepali culture. In 2013, Sherry recieved the International Career Achievement Award from the Pratt Institute.
Scope and Content
This multi-format collection is comprised of audiovisual recordings, newspaper clippings, photographic prints, color slides, and biographies documenting the history and cultural activities of the Dance Theater of Nepal. Sherry Onna Handlin, the creator of the collection, amassed these materials from her own personal experiences in Nepal and her administrative roles with the Theater between the years of 1994 and 2010. All of the materials, except for the artist profiles; which were arranged by format, have retained their original order.
While the collection documents the dance group as a whole, the majority of it is dedicated to the individual artists. Included are twenty-two folders for each artist including photographs, newspaper clippings, audio and visual recordings, as well as manuscript items such as awards, letters of recommendation, and biographies. The folder created for Binod Oli and Devi was received with no materials but there is one color slide of Binod Oli (AFC 2011/002: 027), see Box 5. The success of the group is captured in a variety of newspapers, newspaper clippings and ephemera which ranges from 1995-2010. There are also pamphlets and brochures highlighting some of the country’s most revered tourist destinations.
Sherry requested that the thumb drive of photos, depicting the Dance Theater of Nepal and its performers, be returned to her after processing. She has also chosen to keep the collection open for further accruals. The materials are written in both English and Nepali.
Container List
- Series 1: Manuscripts
  - Subseries A: Administration
    - General scope and content note, 1970s-2010 (Box-folder 1/1)
      The general scope and content note was written by the donor, Sherry Onna Handlin. There are multiple copies of the document with handwritten notes. It also includes an inventory list and an access and restrictions statement for the collection.
    - New York Public Library, general scope and content, 1996-2005 (Box-folder 1/2)
      Inventory, catalog and other materials pertaining to the donation of the collection to the New York Public Library, Special Collections, Dance Division at the Lincoln Center on May 25, 2005.
    - DTON overview, 2000-2010 (Box-folder 1/3)
      Original documents and photocopies of flyers, programs, articles, letters and other information pertaining to the origins of the dance group; its founders and artists, the country of Nepal and its folk and musical traditions.
    - Biographical summary: Raj Kapoor, 1980s-2000s (Box-folder 1/4)
      Includes copies of newspaper clippings, performance programs and flyers, photocopied colored photographs, and letters of recommendation.
    - Biographical summary: Sherry Onna Handlin, 1970s-1990s (Box-folder 1/5)
      Includes a resume, newspaper clippings, photocopied colored photographs, flyers, programs, certificates and letters of recommendation.
    - Dance and visual arts classes, 2004; 2009 (Box-folder 1/6)
      Contains a syllabi, advertisements, students' work, and thank you letters from students of Sherry's art class at Pratt Institute and University Settlement, New York.
    - Ephemera, 1990s-2000s (Box-folder 1/7)
      Postcards, flyers and photocopied colored photographs of the artists in the Dance Theater of Nepal.
  - Subseries B: Artist profiles and works
    - Two Faces of a Coin, 2008 (Box-folder 1/8)
      The monograph is written by Nepali native, Unnati ‘Sheela’ Bohara, poet, author, and song-writer. It is based on husband and wife relationships in a male-dominated Hindu society.
      In English.
    - Love from across the ocean, 2010 (Box-folder 1/9)
      The monograph is written in Nepali by Santu Maya Adhikara Ghimire.
    - Global Echoes, and Sunkeshari, undated (Box-folder 1/10)
      Two-page photocopy of the artists' profiles and a list of recordings by, Suraj Nepal and Shubha Bahadur. See AFC 2011/002: SR03-SR04.
    - Baskota Shambhujeet, undated (Box-folder 1/11)
      Two-page photocopy of the artist's profile and a list of contents. See AFC 2011/002: SR01 and AFC 2011/002: MV06.
    - Subarna Chhetri and Ram Raj, undated (Box-folder 1/12)
      Photocopy of the artists' profiles and list of contents. See AFC 2011/002: MV08 and AFC 2011/002: MV10.
    - Tsewang Dorje, undated (Box-folder 1/13)
      Photocopy of the artist's profile. See AFC 2011/002: MV09 and AFC 2011/002: MV15.
    - Goma Gurung, 1996-1998, 2000, 2002-2003; 2005-2010 (Box-folder 1/14)
      Includes a photocopy of the artist's profile and a list of materials which includes pubilicty photographs, newspaper clippings, and awards belonging to Goma Gurung. See AFC 2011/002: MV07 and AFC 2011/002: MV11.
    - Krishna Gurung, 2009 (Box-folder 1/15)
      Photocopy of the artist's profile and a list of contents along with a copy of his monograph entitled, Dhorje. It is about a young man who leaves his family in Nepal and travels to New York in search of a better life.
      In Nepali.
    - Ramesh Gurung, undated (Box-folder 1/16)
      Photocopy of the artist's profile and a list of contents. See Box 3 for color prints and AFC 2011/002: MV12 and AFC 2011/002: MV13 for recordings.
    - Deepak Koirala, 2010 (Box-folder 2/17)
      Photocopy of the artist's profile and an inventory of contents in the folder including newspaper clippings, and a program book highlighting Deepak Koirala and his career. See AFC 2011/002: MV16 and AFC 2011/002: MV17.
    - Dharambir Lama, undated (Box-folder 2/18)
      Two-page photocopy of the artist's profile and a list of contents along with a biographical sketch of Dharambir Lama. See AFC 2011/002: MV18.
    - Raja Mahat, 2010 (Box-folder 2/19)
      Newspaper clippings in Nepali.
    - Ram A. Nagarkoti, 2000 (Box-folder 2/20)
      Two-page photocopy of the artist's profile and a list of contents including an award, a flyer and a photographic print of the artist. See AFC 2011/002: MV19.
    - Binod Oli and Devi, undated (Box-folder 2/21)
      Folder received with no content.
    - Binita Poudyal, undated (Box-folder 2/22)
      Two-page photocopy of the artist's profile and list of contents including a performance resume. See AFC 2011/002: MV20.
    - Charan Pradhan, undated (Box-folder 2/23)
      Two-page photocopy of the artist's profile and a list of contents along with photocopies of photographic prints. See AFC 2011/002: MV21.
    - Basanti D. Rai, 2002-2003; 2008-2010 (Box-folder 2/24)
      Two-page photocopy of the artist's profile and a list of contents along with photocopies of flyers, awards and photographic prints.
      Oversized newspapers separated to Box 6
    - Ang Kami Sherpa, undated (Box-folder 2/25)
      Photocopy of the artist's profile and an inventory of items along with a black and white photocopy of the artist. See AFC 2011/002: PH215 and AFC 2011/002: PH216.
    - Gagan Shrestha and Harish Mathema, 2008 (Box-folder 2/26)
      Two-page photocopy of the artist's profile and a list of contents including a letter of recommendation. See AFC 2011/002: MV22.
    - Shisir Shrestha, undated (Box-folder 2/27)
      Two-page photocopy of the artist's profile and a list of contents. See AFC 2011/002: MV23 and AFC 2011/002: SR02.
    - Hari Siwakoti, 1999 (Box-folder 2/28)
      Photocopy of a New York Times article about Hari Siwakoti.
    - Shashi Kala Tiwari, 1982, 1992; 1996-1997 (Box-folder 2/29)
      Photocopy of the artist's profile including original brochures of various art galleries highlighting Shashi Kala Tiwari's paintings.
    - Prajwal Vajracharya, 2004, 2008-2009; undated (Box-folder 2/30)
      Photocopy of the artist's profile including articles, postcards and flyers about Newar Buddhist tradition and Dance Mandal.
  - Subseries C: Newspaper clippings and promotional materials
    - Nepal, 1995-2010 (1/3) (Box-folder 2/31)
      Clippings from Nepali newspapers, from October 1995-November 2010. The majority of clippings are written in Nepali.
    - Nepal, 1995-2010 (2/3) (Box-folder 2/32)
    - Nepal, 1995-2010 (3/3) (Box-folder 2/33)
    - Nepal's current events, 1995-2007 (Box-folder 2/34)
      Printouts and newspaper clippings on Nepal and its current events, 1995-2007. In English, except for 3 newspaper clippings in Nepali.
    - Promotional materials, 1998-1999, 2001, 2004, 2006; 2008-2009 (1/3) (Box-folder 2/35)
      Originals and photocopies of photographic prints, advertisements, postcards, brochures, newspaper clippings and related programs to DTON. Materials are in English.
    - Promotional materials, 1998, 2003, 2005; undated (2/3) (Box-folder 2/36)
      Brochures, magazines, and postcards of Nepal.
    - Promotional materials, undated (3/3) (Box-folder 2/37)
      Brochures and postcards of Nepal including a handwritten postcard to Sherry Onna Handlin.
- Series 2: Sound recordings
  - Global Instrumental, 2010, 1 sound disc (CD): digital; 4 3/4 in. (Item-id AFC 2011/002: SR01)
    Audio recording of a collaboration by Shambhujeet Baskota, Niraj Singh, Sauryjeet and Sandeep Mitra. See Folder 12.
  - Samamutu, undated, 1 sound disc (CD): digital; 4 3/4 in. (Item-id AFC 2011/002: SR02)
    An audio disc of Shisir Shrestha’s band, Samamutu. The recordings feature a number of traditional Nepali instruments, including the tungna and madal. See Folder 28.
  - Global Echoes: Musical Harmony in Esraj, 2010, 1 sound disc (CD): digital; 4 3/4 in. (Item-id AFC 2011/002: SR03)
    Includes seven musical renditions of Nepali music by Suraj Nepal. The madal and sarangi, which are traditional Nepali instruments, are not listed as instruments used in the renditions. See Folder 11.
  - Sunkeshari, 2003, 1 sound disc (CD): digital; 4 3/4 in. (Item-id AFC 2011/002: SR04)
    Sunkeshari is the tale of a beautiful girl with cascading, golden hair. The tale is rendered in song and attempts to pay homage to her beauty. The disc has a number of tracks that is dedicated to the tale. See Folder 11.
  - Kathmandu Embrace: Music from the Himalayan Land of Nepal, 2007, 1 sound disc (CD): digital; 4 3/4 in. (Item-id AFC 2011/002: SR05)
    A collection of folk tunes and melodies from the Himalayan Land of Nepal by Arjun Gurung and Raj Kapoor.
  - Newar Music, undated, 2 sound discs (CD): digital; 4 3/4 in. (Item-id AFC 2011/002: SR06-SR07)
    Music from the Newar (Nepalese people) of Kathmandu Valley. The music involves chanting accompanied by a number of different wind and percussion instruments.
- Series 3: Graphic images
  - Subseries A: Prints
    - New York Public Library Archives Project, 2005, 6 color prints (Box-folder 3/38)
      AFC 2011/002: PH001-PH005B: Photographs of NYPL collection and its creators.
    - Sherry Onna Handlin, 1988/1989, 1 black-and-white print (Box-folder 3/39)
      AFC 2011/002: PH006: Photograph of Sherry Onna Handlin working with her collection.
    - Trip to archives in Dharamsala, India, 1994, 8 color prints (Box-folder 3/40)
      AFC 2011/002: PH007-PH014: Photographs of Sherry’s trip in India en route to Nepal.
    - DTON performers, 2008, undated, 3 color prints (Box-folder 3/41)
      AFC 2011/002: PH028-PH030: Photographs of the Dance Theater of Nepal performers in New York City. See Box 5 for slides.
    - DTON performance at various locations, 1990s-2010, 79 color prints (Box-folder 3/42)
      AFC 2011/002: PH031-PH103: Photographs of the Dance Theater of Nepal performers at various venues, including a few photographs of Sherry with the NYPL collection.
    - Nepal, 1994, 33 color prints (Box-folder 3/43)
      AFC 2011/002: PH104-PH136: Photographs of Sherry’s trip to Nepal.
    - Nepali community, 1990s-2010, 14 color prints (Box-folder 4/44)
      AFC 2011/002: PH137-PH150: Photographs of the Nepalese community at various functions in the United States.
    - DTON performers, 1997-1999; 2003-2005; 2008, undated, 2 black-and-white prints; 68 color prints (Box-folder 4/45)
      AFC 2011/002: PH151-PH220: Photographs of the artists and organizers of the Dance Theater of Nepal.
  - Subseries B: Color slides
    - Performers, 1997-1998, undated, 13 35mm color slides (Box 5)
      AFC 2011/002: PH015-PH027: Performers from the Dance Theater of Nepal in New York City.
    - Mt. Everest, 1998, 5 35mm color slides
      AFC 2011/002: PH285-PH289: Images of individuals climbing Mt. Everest.
  - Subseries C: Digital images
    - Dance Mandal in Portland, Oregon, 2009, AFC 2011/002: PH221-PH284; 1 optical disc; 63 digital color photographs
      Photographs of Sherry Onna Handlin, Prajwal Vajrachara, an administrator at the Newari Temple, a Newar Buddhist priest, and Charya Nritya (DTON dancer) at the opening of Newari Temple which is the first Nepali temple in Portland, Oregon.
    - DTON, 1 thumb drive; 175 digital color photographs
      An assortment of digital color photographs documenting the activities and performers of the Dance Theater of Nepal.
- Series 4: Moving images
  - Subseries A: Videocassettes
    - World Music Institute presents, The Raj Kapoor Ensemble Music and Dance of Nepal, 1998, AFC 2011/002: MV01; 1 videocassette (VHS): analog
      Raj Kapoor Ensemble Symphony performs at the Space Concert on October 17, 1998. Video by Tanya Reeves.
    - Raj Kapoor Ensemble of Nepal, Smithsonian, Washington, D.C., 1999, AFC 2011/002: MV02; 1 videocassette (VHS; 60 mins.): analog.
      Raj Kapoor and the dance theater perform at the Smithsonian on August 14, 1999.
    - Subha Ratri, November 29, 2003, AFC 2011/002: MV03; 1 videocassette (VHS): analog.
      Recording of the 'Y' Theater-Ed. Alliance New York City, Benefit Concert.
    - Raj Kapoor and Dancers... Live from Nepal present, Traditional Folk and Classical Dances of Nepal, undated, AFC 2011/002: MV04; 1 videocassette (VHS): analog.
    - Dance Mandal presents, Charya Nritya: The Tantric Buddhist Dane of Nepal, Tantrisch-buddhistische Tanze aus Nepal, undated, AFC 2011/002: MV05; 1 videocassette (VHS): analog.
  - Subseries B: Optical discs
    - Aasakti, undated, AFC 2011/002: MV06; 1 videodisc (DVD): digital; 4 3/4 in.
      Recording of a number of music videos which were filmed in the U.S. and Nepal. The themes are centered around courtship and romance. Shambhujit Vaskota directed the music for the video.
    - American Nepalese Friendship Society (ANFS) celebrates Napali New Year 2066, AFC 2011/002: MV07; 1 videodisc (DVD): digital; 4 3/4 in.
      Recording of Nepal's New Year, 2066 celebrated on April 11, 2009, at the Dhaka Club, Woodside, New York. Track four was written and sung by Goma Gurung.
    - 11th Presentation of New York Kalamanch to Library of Congress, 2010, AFC 2011/002: MV08; 1 videodisc (DVD): digital; 4 3/4 in.
      Recording of the Kalamanch's awards ceremony with intermittent song and dance, October 8th, 2010 at the Library of Congress, Part 1.
    - DREAM, undated, AFC 2011/002: MV09; 1 videodisc (DVD): digital; 4 3/4 in.
      Short film about an ordinary guy on his commute home and his recurring nightmares. Filmed and edited by Tsewang Dorjee.
    - 11th Presentation of New York Kalamanch to Library of Congress, 2010, AFC 2011/002: MV10; 1 videodisc (DVD): digital; 4 3/4 in.
      Recording of the Kalamanch's awards ceremony with intermittent song and dance, October 8th, 2010 at the Library of Congress, Part 2.
    - America-Nepali Friendship Society, Inc. Nepali New Year Cultural Program, 2064, AFC 2011/002: MV11; 1 videodisc (DVD): digital; 4 3/4 in.
      Recording of Nepal's New Year, 2064 in New York, April 07, 2007 at the Dhaka Club, Woodside, New York, Part 2. See Folder 15.
    - The Gurung (Tamu) Society, USA: Kancha Chyu Lhochhar year of The Mouse, December 29, 2007, New York. Video by Moktan Digital, AFC 2011/002: MV12; 1 videodisc (DVD): digital; 4 3/4 in.
      See Folder 17.
    - An Indreni audio music presents, aming Selo remix, undated, AFC 2011/002: MV13; 1 videodisc (DVD): digital; 4 3/4 in.
    - Gurung (Tamu) Society Inc. USA presents, Khi-Lhochhar (Year of The Dog), undated, AFC 2011/002: MV14; 1 videodisc (DVD): digital; 4 3/4 in.
      See on Folder 17.
    - Tsewang music video, undated, AFC 2011/002: MV15; 1 videodisc (DVD): digital; 4 3/4 in.
      Music video of a romantic song that has clips of a couple dancing around New York City. The video was recorded in Nepali. See Folder 14.
    - 5th International Folk Festival for Peace, 5th March to 14th March 2010, Kathmandu-Palpa-Pokhara-Surkhet, Nepal, AFC 2011/002: MV16; 1 videodisc (DVD): digital; 4 3/4 in.
      The Festival was organized by the Everest Nepal Cultural Group. The recording includes indoor and outdoor concerts, as well as a parade. See Folder 18.
    - 4th International Folk Festival for Peace 2008 from May 31st to June 07th, AFC 2011/002: MV17; 1 videodisc (DVD): digital; 4 3/4 in.
      The Festival was organized by the Everest Nepal Cultural Group. Recording includes multiple concerts, celebrations, and parades in cities such as Kathmandu, Palpa, Pokhara, Lalitpur, and Trishuli. Participating countries include Nepal, United States of America, India, Latvia, Costa Rico, Israel, Sri Lanka. See Folder 18.
    - Dharam Bir Lama, undated, AFC 2011/002: MV18; 1 videodisc (DVD): digital; 4 3/4 in.
      Performance profile of Dharam Bir Lama that includes a number of his own personal performances. In Nepali. See Folder 19.
    - Ista-Mitra, Rakshita presents, Ista Mitra, undated, AFC 2011/002: MV19; 1 videodisc (DVD): digital; 4 3/4 in.
      The first Nepali film produced in America. The film is based on a courtship and is filmed in New York City and D.C. A number of DTON artists assisted in its production. In English. See Folder 21.
    - Binita Poudyal and Friends present: Kathmandu Sanjh, 2009, AFC 2011/002: MV20; 1 videodisc (DVD): digital; 4 3/4 in.
      Performance of Nepali folk music and dance at the Shangri La Restaurant in Queens, New York on March 28, 2009. See Folder 24.
    - Charan Pradhan Video Interview: Video and Interview of Charan Pradhan, undated, AFC 2011/002: MV21; 1 videodisc (DVD): digital; 4 3/4 in.
      Sherry interviews Charan about his work with dance and the city of Nepal. In English. 1 DVD. See Folder 24.
    - Nepali Cultural Program, October 28, 2000, Virginia, AFC 2011/002: MV22; 1 videodisc (DVD): digital; 4 3/4 in.
      Instrumentalists include Gagan Shrestha and Nhuchhe Narayan. See Folder 27.
    - Tunes of Nepal, 1996, AFC 2011/002: MV23; 1 videodisc (DVD): digital; 4 3/4 in.
      Shisir's group, Samamutu, plays traditional musical performance. It features instruments such the madal, sarangi, and the tungna. Shisir Shrestha is the musical director and produced by Sa Ma Mu Tu.
    - GNBC Dashak Saanjh, Nepali Cultural Program, September 11, 1999, Boston, AFC 2011/002: MV24; 1 videodisc (DVD): digital; 4 3/4 in.
      The event took place on September 11, 1999 in Boston. It was hosted by the Greater Boston Nepali community which is part of the Nepali cultural program. The performance includes traditional song and dance, with some presentations in Nepali. Shisir Shrestha is the music director. In English and Nepali. See Folder 28.
    - Instruments of Asia and the Pacific, undated, AFC 2011/002: MV25; 1 videodisc (DVD): digital; 4 3/4 in.
      Educational video on different string, wind, and percussion instruments in Asia and the Pacific. The first section of the video focuses on Nepal. Shisir Shrestha is the music director. In English. See Folder 28.
    - Dance Theater of Nepal, 1996; 1998; 2003, AFC 2011/002: MV26; 1 videodisc (DVD): digital; 4 3/4 in.